The Victor D'Amico Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series V. Art Barge, 1950s-2011 (bulk 1955-1980s)
  - Workshops for senior citizens (4 of 4), 1977-1979; Course descriptions and announcements, class presentation, Director's report (Box 32, Folder V.136)
  - Grade school teachers classes, 1977; Photographic contact sheet (Box 32, Folder V.137)
  - Grant suggestions and materials, 1977, 1979; Applications and information on the National Endowment for the Humanities and National Endowment for the Arts grants opportunities (Box 32, Folder V.138)
  - Receipts for contributions, 1977, 1980 (Box 32, Folder V.139)
  - Benefit performances, 1977-1994; Programs for benefit events held at the Art Barge and elsewhere (Box 32, Folder V.140)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1978; Completed grant application form (Box 32, Folder V.141)
  - Letters in response to correspondence re: New York State funding for the arts, 1978; Form letters (Box 32, Folder V.142)
  - Helena Rubinstein Foundation, 1978-1981; Correspondence and supporting materials for grant received to fund summer programs (Box 32, Folder V.143)
  - Notices of events, mailing and supply lists, local accommodations, 1978-1985, undated (Box 32, Folder V.144)
  - Administrative correspondence, 1979; Re: donations, bills to be paid (Box 32, Folder V.145)
  - Clippings, 1979-1984 (Box 32, Folder V.146)
  - Videotaped classes and interviews, [1980s]; Standard VHS cassette: "#1 Marcus screenwriting; beach, folk music (DiPirro), Weldon" (Box 32, Folder V.147)
  - Videotaped classes and interviews, [1980s]; Standard VHS cassette: "#2 Petulia; Bettina's class; Arlette's class; Bernice's class" (Box 32, Folder V.148)
  - Videotaped classes and interviews, [1980s]; Standard VHS cassette: "#3 Arlette's class; sand sculpture (Mabel, Chris), Bernice's class Coelho's class; beach" (Box 32, Folder V.149)
  - Videotaped classes and interviews, [1980s]; Standard VHS cassette: "#4 Tyson, Bigar and Frankle; John Tobias; Arlette interview" (Box 32, Folder V.150)
  - Videotaped classes and interviews, [1980s]; Standard VHS cassette: "#5 Marcus "Woman in the Dune"; Nicole's class; Mabel home; Teddy (studio)" (Box 32, Folder V.151)
  - Videotaped classes and interviews, [1980s]; Standard VHS cassette: "#6 Music 1 hr.: Zooey and Albin; Music 1 hr: Victoria and Michael" (Box 32, Folder V.152)
  - Videotaped classes and interviews, [1980s]; Standard VHS cassette: "#7 Victoria and Michael; Tyson birthday; artist and poetry" (Box 33, Folder V.153)
  - Videotaped classes and interviews, [1980s]; Standard VHS cassette: "#8 Arlette 'Animals and art'; Carpentier's class and party" (Box 33, Folder V.154)
  - Letterhead, unidentified sketch, After 1981 (Box 33, Folder V.155)
  - Summer art programs (1 of 2), 1983, 1984, 1986-1990; Annual brochures (Box 33, Folder V.156)
  - Summer art programs (2 of 2), 1998, 2000-2007, 2011; Annual brochures (Box 33, Folder V.157)
  - Children with their art, 1984; B/w prints (Box 33, Folder V.158)
  - "Artists Speak", 1984-1992; Correspondence related to, and photographs of artists who participated in, an Amagansett television program that interviewed artists (Box 33, Folder V.159)
  - "Artists Speak" event: Philip Pearlstein, July 1988; Posters, clipping (Box 71, Folder V.160*)
  - Poster "Exploring the Legends: Guideposts to the future - Victor D'Amico", 1991; Event at MoMA presented by the University Council for Art Education (Box 33, Folder V.161)
- Series VI. Exhibitions, 1938-1969
  The series includes information on exhibitions, both at MoMA and some that circulated, organized by the Department of Education or with its significant collaboration. It includes both numbered MoMA exhibitions and those mounted in the Young People's Gallery and other spaces, which were not included in the Museum's chronological numbering system. The documentation is almost entirely in the form of photographs (installation views, exhibition panels, and individual items on view); there is minimal administrative or organizational information. For exhibitions that circulated to schools, see Series II. New York City High Schools Program. Some folders in Series IV. Children's Art Carnival, and Series III.A. War Veterans' Art Center, may also include exhibition-related information.
  The Young People's Gallery opened at MoMA on November 1, 1939, as a "special exhibition space, designed to serve the needs of art students between the ages of 12 and 18." It was an outgrowth of the New York City High Schools Program (see Series II). All of its rotating exhibitions were "selected for, or by, pupils in the art classes of secondary schools. Occasionally a showing of their own work will be held. Demonstrations in various fields of art will be given by well-known artists and followed by discussion of techniques, media, and other matters of interest to young art students." (MoMA press release, "Young People's Gallery Opens at Museum of Modern Art with Unusual Exhibition," October 30, 1939). Special equipment used for display in the gallery was designed by D'Amico, including convertible easels and easily reconfigured chains of desks.
  The subseries is organized chronologically by exhibition. For many exhibitions, there are two sets of images: one of mounted prints from various series of albums and one of unmounted prints. These have been combined into a single folder where space allows.
  - Machine Art[MoMA Exh. #73, March 7-March 31, 1938], Installation views; from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions": mounted prints (Box 33, Folder VI.1)
  - Young People’s Gallery, 1939-1940; Includes installation views from We Like Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #120, December 27, 1940-January 12, 1941];Creative Growth, Childhood to Maturity[MoMA Exh. #92, November 1, 1939-January 5, 1940]; as well as images of a cantilevered easel designed by D'Amico: b/w prints (Box 33, Folder VI.2)
  - Young People's Gallery, [1940s]; Press release, drafts of wall text; includes materials re:Work from Art Classes[MoMA Exh. #422, September 30-October 30, 1949] (Box 33, Folder VI.3)
  - Young People’s Gallery, [1940s]; Poster competition open to art students in Greater New York high schools. From an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery": mounted b/w prints (Box 33, Folder VI.4)
  - Creative Growth, Childhood to Maturity[MoMA Exh. #92, November 1, 1939-January 5, 1940], Installation views, photographs of objects in the exhibition; from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery": mounted b/w prints (Box 33, Folder VI.5)
  - Creative Growth, Childhood to Maturity[MoMA Exh. #92, November 1, 1939-January 5, 1940], Installation views, photographs of objects in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 33, Folder VI.6)
  - 12 Favorites: Paintings Selected by Students from the Museum Collection[MoMA Exh. #96, January 31-March 1, 1940], Installation views; from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery": mounted b/w prints (Box 33, Folder VI.7)
  - 12 Favorites: Paintings Selected by Students from the Museum Collection[MoMA Exh. #96, January 31-March 1, 1940], Visitors in the gallery: b/w prints (Box 34, Folder VI.8)
  - Visual and Non-Visual Expression in Art[MoMA Exh. #101, March 6-May 1, 1940], Installation views, photographs of objects in the exhibition; from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery": mounted b/w prints (Box 34, Folder VI.9)
  - Visual and Non-Visual Expression in Art[MoMA Exh. #101, March 6-May 1, 1940], Installation views and photographs of objects in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 34, Folder VI.10)
  - Twenty Centuries of Mexican Art[MoMA Exh. #106, May 15-September 30, 1940], Photographs of objects in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 34, Folder VI.11)
  - Modern Interiors[MoMA Exh. #109, October 3-November 2, 1940], Installation views, photographs of objects in the exhibition: unmounted b/w prints and those from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions” (Box 34, Folder VI.12)
  - Graphic Arts: Designing a Stage Setting[MoMA Exh. #112, November 4-November 11, 1940], Exhibition panels, photographs of individual objects; from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions": mounted b/w prints (Box 34, Folder VI.13)
  - Graphic Arts: Designing a Stage Setting[MoMA Exh. #112, November 4-November 11, 1940], Photographs of exhibition panels and individual objects from circulating exhibition: b/w prints (Box 34, Folder VI.14)
  - We Like Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #120, December 27, 1940-January 12, 1941], Exhibition planned by students from high schools in MoMA's educational program. Installation views, photographs of jury of students working with D'Amico to select items; from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery": mounted b/w prints (Box 34, Folder VI.15)
  - We Like Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #120, December 27, 1940-January 12, 1941], Exhibition planned by students from high schools in MoMA's educational program. Includes installation views, photographs of jury of students working with D'Amico to select items: b/w prints (Box 34, Folder VI.16)
  - Book mock-up "We Like Modern Art (Introductory Series to the Modern Arts, No. 1)”, [1940]; Pencil-lettered, comb-bound volume with layout marked for photographs and text (Box 34, Folder VI.17)
  - Animals in Art[MoMA Exh. #136, July 1-July 15, 1941], Photographs of exhibition panels: unmounted b/w prints and those from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions” (Box 34, Folder VI.18)
  - Shapes of Things[MoMA Exh. #137, July 15-July 28, 1941], Photographs of exhibition panels: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions" (Box 34, Folder VI.19)
  - Shapes of Things[MoMA Exh. #137, July 15-July 28, 1941], Also identified here as “Young People's rotating exhibition #32.” Photographs of exhibition panels: b/w prints (Box 34, Folder VI.20)
  - Abstract Painting[MoMA Exh. #137, July 15-July 28, 1941], Photographs of exhibition panels: unmounted b/w prints and those from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions” (Box 34, Folder VI.21)
  - Preliminary Course of the Bauhaus[MoMA Exh. #141, July 29-August 11, 1941], Installation views, photographs of objects in the exhibition: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions" (Box 34, Folder VI.22)
  - Lettering and Arrangements in Poster Design[MoMA Exh. #143, August 12-August 25, 1941], Installation views, photographs of objects in the exhibition: unmounted b/w prints and those from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions” (Box 34, Folder VI.23)
  - Ancestral Sources of Modern Painting[MoMA Exh. #144, August 26-September 15, 1941], Installation views: unmounted b/w prints and those from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions” (Box 34, Folder VI.24)
  - Children of England Paint[MoMA Exh. #156, November 6-November 30, 1941], Photographs of paintings in the exhibition: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery" (Box 35, Folder VI.25)
  - The Museum in Education[June 19-August 3, 1941], Installation views: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions" (Box 35, Folder VI.26)
  - Map of cities interested in small exhibitions, [1941]; From an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions": mounted b/w print (Box 35, Folder VI.27)
  - Graphic Arts, [1941]; Photographs of exhibition panels: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions" (Box 35, Folder VI.28)
  - Pictures for Children[MoMA Exh. #164, December 10, 1941-Jan 25, 1942], Photographs of paintings in the exhibition, installation views: unmounted b/w prints and those from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery" (Box 35, Folder VI.29)
  - Children's Festival of Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #173, March 11-May 10, 1942], Photograph of exhibition opening panel from the first iteration of the Children’s Art Carnival (see Series IV.A.i): mounted b/w print (Box 35, Folder VI.30)
  - Anti-Hoarding Pictures by New York School Children[MoMA Exh. #180, May 13-June 8, 1942], Photographs of objects in the exhibition: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions" (Box 35, Folder VI.31)
  - Salvage Posters by New York High School Students[MoMA Exh. #187, June 24-September 3, 1942], Photographs of objects in the exhibition: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions" (Box 35, Folder VI.32)
  - Work of New York Public School Classes, June 2-28, 1942, Photographs of objects in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 35, Folder VI.33)
  - Bambi: The Making of an Animated Sound Picture[MoMA Exh. #189, July 15-August 20, 1942], Photographs of visitors attending the exhibition: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery" (Box 35, Folder VI.34)
  - Planning a Modern House[MoMA Exh. #191, August 25-September 21, 1942], Photographs of exhibition panels: unmounted b/w prints and mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions" (Box 35, Folder VI.35)
  - Modern Architecture for the Modern School[MoMA Exh. #194, September 16-September 30, 1942], Photographs of panels as installed at Fieldston School and of a student working on the exhibition: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Miscellaneous Circulating Exhibitions" (Box 35, Folder VI.36)
  - Art of Two Cities: Chicago and New York[MoMA Exh. #200, October 14-November 15, 1942], Photographs of paintings from the exhibition: unmounted b/w prints and those from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery" (Box 35, Folder VI.37)
  - Children's Painting and the War[MoMA Exh. #206, November 18-December 13, 1942], Photographs of paintings from the exhibition: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery" (Box 35, Folder VI.38)
  - USO exhibition:Understanding Children's Art, [July 1943]; Photographs of exhibition panels: b/w prints (Box 35, Folder VI.39)
  - USO exhibition:Magic in Your Hands, [August 1943]; Photographs of exhibition panels: b/w prints (Box 35, Folder VI.40)
  - USO exhibition:Your Home - Your Design for Living, [August 1943]; Photographs of exhibition panels: b/w prints (Box 35, Folder VI.41)
  - USO exhibition:Looking at Art of Latin America, [October 1943]; Made for the USO Division, National Board YWCA, by the Educational Program, MoMA, and the Committee on Art in American Education and Society: mounted b/w prints removed from post album (Box 35, Folder VI.42)
  - USO exhibition:Looking at Art of Latin America, [October 1943]; From an exhibition made for the USO division, National Board, YWCA, by the Educational Program of MoMA and the Committee on Art in American Education and Society Exhibition panels: b/w prints (Box 35, Folder VI.43)
  - The Arts in Therapy[MoMA Exh. #216, February 3-March 7, 1943], Photographs of exhibition panels, objects in the exhibition: mounted b/w prints from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery" (Box 35, Folder VI.44)
  - The Arts in Therapy[MoMA Exh. #216, February 3-March 7, 1943], Stills from motion picture created for the exhibition by D'Amico, Bernard Sanders, and Charles Cook: b/w prints (Box 36, Folder VI.45)
  - Art Shows for U.S.O. Centers[MoMA Exh. #238, August 4-September 26, 1943], Installation views that include some exhibitions documented in folders VI.39-41: b/w prints (Box 36, Folder VI.46)
  - Young Negro Art[MoMA Exh. #243, October 26-November 28, 1943], Photographs of objects in the exhibition, guests at exhibition opening including D'Amico: b/w prints (Box 36, Folder VI.47)
  - Posters[MoMA Exh. #258e, May 24-September 17, 1944], Color glass-mounted slides (Box 36, Folder VI.48)
  - Soviet Children's Art[MoMA Exh. #260, September 19-November 19, 1944], Photographs of paintings in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 36, Folder VI.49)
  - Modern Art for Young People[MoMA Exh. #279, February 21-March 11, 1945], 1944; Photographs of exhibition panels, installation views at Board of Education headquarters: unmounted b/w prints and those from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery" (Box 36, Folder VI.50)
  - Teaching Elements of Design to Children[MoMA Exh. #288, May 16-June 10, 1945], Photographs of exhibition panels; from an album "Educational Program Photographs - Exhibitions in the Young People's Gallery": mounted b/w prints (Box 36, Folder VI.51)
  - Art for War Veterans[MoMA Exh. #297, September 26-November 25, 1945], Photographs of individual art pieces, students at work, exhibition panels, installation views: mounted b/w prints removed from post-bound album labeled "Bk. II" (Box 36, Folder VI.52)
  - Art for War Veterans[MoMA Exh. #297, September 26-November 25, 1945], Installation views, photographs of exhibition panels: b/w prints (Box 36, Folder VI.53)
  - Art for War Veterans[MoMA Exh. #297, September 26-November 25, 1945], Photographs of objects in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 36, Folder VI.54)
  - Art for War Veterans[MoMA Exh. #297, September 26-November 25, 1945], Photographs of exhibition panels: b/w prints (Box 37, Folder VI.55)
  - Art for War Veterans[MoMA Exh. #297, September 26-November 25, 1945], 1945-1948; Includes photographs of students at work, objects from the exhibition, panels and installation views, visitors at the opening: mounted and unmounted b/w prints (Box 37, Folder VI.56)
  - Creative Art by American Children[MoMA Exh. #305, January 15-March 3, 1946], Photographs of objects in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 37, Folder VI.57)
  - Designed for Children[MoMA Exh. #320, June 11-October 6, 1946], 1945-1946; Includes draft texts, draft and final press release, expense list, loan receipts, designs for cases and exhibition layout (Box 37, Folder VI.58)
  - Designed for Children[MoMA Exh. #320, June 11-October 6, 1946], Installation views: mounted b/w prints previously removed from album (Box 37, Folder VI.59)
  - Designed for Children[MoMA Exh. #320, June 11-October 6, 1946], 1946-1953; Includes images from other design-related exhibitions, previously culled by Teachers College: b/w prints (Box 37, Folder VI.60)
  - On Being a Cartoonist[MoMA Exh. #333, October 15-November 24, 1946], Photographs of objects in the exhibition: photoreproductions (Box 37, Folder VI.61)
  - Children's Holiday Fair of Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #338, December 3, 1946-January 5, 1947], B/w prints mounted on pages previously removed from album (Box 37, Folder VI.62)
  - Children's Holiday Fair of Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #338, December 3, 1946-January 5, 1947], Photographs of children at work: b/w prints mounted on pages previously removed from album (Box 37, Folder VI.63)
  - Children's Holiday Fair of Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #338, December 3, 1946-January 5, 1947], Photographs of children at work: b/w prints mounted on pages previously removed from album (Box 37, Folder VI.64)
  - Children's Holiday Fair of Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #338, December 3, 1946-January 5, 1947], Installation views: b/w prints mounted on pages previously removed from album (Box 37, Folder VI.65)
  - Children's Holiday Fair of Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #338, December 3, 1946-January 5, 1947], Photographs of children at work, objects in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 37, Folder VI.66)
  - Exhibitions of teaching techniques, at MoMA and elsewhere, April 1947, undated; Correspondence, labels (Box 37, Folder VI.67)
  - Paintings by French Children[MoMA Exh. #366, January 13-March 21, 1948], Photographs of paintings in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 37, Folder VI.68)
  - Work from War Veterans' Art Center[MoMA Exh. #383, September 1-October 10, 1948], Photographs of woodworking objects from the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 37, Folder VI.69)
  - Work from War Veterans' Art Center[MoMA Exh. #383, September 1-October 10, 1948], Photographs of ceramics and jewelry from the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 37, Folder VI.70)
  - Work from War Veterans' Art Center[MoMA Exh. #383, September 1-October 10, 1948], Photographs of panels and objects in the exhibition: photoreproductions (Box 38, Folder VI.71)
  - Work from War Veterans' Art Center[MoMA Exh. #383, September 1-October 10, 1948], Photographs of panels and objects in the exhibition: photoreproductions pasted up on boards, photostats (Box 38, Folder VI.72)
  - Work from War Veterans' Art Center[MoMA Exh. #383, September 1-October 10, 1948], Photographs of individual objects from the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 38, Folder VI.73)
  - Work from War Veterans' Art Center[MoMA Exh. #383, September 1-October 10, 1948], Photographs of visitors at the opening of the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 38, Folder VI.74)
  - Art in the Neighborhood: Focus on World Unity[MoMA Exh. #392, November 10, 1948-November 28, 1948], Photographs of panels from the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 38, Folder VI.75)
  - Paintings by Japanese Children, Aged 6-12[MoMA Exh. #428, November 2-November 27, 1949], Photographs of paintings in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 38, Folder VI.76)
  - How to Make a Silk Screen Print, by Harry Sternberg, [1949-1950]; "Exhibition for the Department of Education": b/w prints removed from post album (Box 38, Folder VI.77)
  - Exhibition planning, 1950s; Includes images of staff selecting objects for exhibitions including The Art Teaching of Belle Boas[MoMA Exh. #553, March 17-May 2, 1954] and Children's Art Carnival; images previously culled by Teachers College: b/w prints (Box 38, Folder VI.78)
  - We Create for Pleasure[MoMA Exh. #499, January 23-March 2, 1952], 1951-1952; Exhibition of art work by adult students of the People's Art Center: drafts of text, press release, comments by students (Box 38, Folder VI.79)
  - Human Quality in Creative Experience[MoMA Exh. #505, March 20-April 20, 1952], 1951-1952; Draft texts, loan receipts (Box 38, Folder VI.80)
  - Human Quality in Creative Experience[MoMA Exh. #505, March 20-April 20, 1952], Mock-up of exhibition layout (Box 38, Folder VI.81)
  - Human Quality in Creative Experience[MoMA Exh. #505, March 20-April 20, 1952], Draft text for panels: originals and carbons; installation views: b/w prints (Box 38, Folder VI.82)
  - Human Quality in Creative Experience[MoMA Exh. #505, March 20-April 20, 1952], Exhibition labels, keyed on back to parts of the exhibition (Box 38, Folder VI.83)
  - Human Quality in Creative Experience[MoMA Exh. #505, March 20-April 20, 1952], November 5, 1956; Later documentation from a traveling version of the exhibition: guide to installing the exhibition, including checklist of panels, installation photographs, suggestions for related art activities. Includes receipt from unnamed Atlantic City venue noting condition ("corners and titles somewhat worn") (Box 38, Folder VI.84)
  - Premium Toys Designed for Industry[MoMA Exh. #544, October 13-December 27, 1953], Installation views, photographs of objects in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 38, Folder VI.85)